<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The genealogie of Christianity and of Christians. Declared in a sermon at Mercers Chappel before the Right Honourable the Lord Maior of the City of London, April 28. 1650 and now thus published for the undeceiving of those, who say they are Christians, and are not, but do lie; and for the establishment and encouragement of those, who having named the name of Christ, do indeed depart (even in this hour of apostacy) from all iniquity, by C.F. one of the servants of the Lord Jesus Christ in the ministery of the new Testament.</title>
            <author>Feake, Christopher, fl. 1645-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E599_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202091</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862498</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85175)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E599[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The genealogie of Christianity and of Christians. Declared in a sermon at Mercers Chappel before the Right Honourable the Lord Maior of the City of London, April 28. 1650 and now thus published for the undeceiving of those, who say they are Christians, and are not, but do lie; and for the establishment and encouragement of those, who having named the name of Christ, do indeed depart (even in this hour of apostacy) from all iniquity, by C.F. one of the servants of the Lord Jesus Christ in the ministery of the new Testament.</title>
                  <author>Feake, Christopher, fl. 1645-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[50] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Cole, at the Printing-Press in Cornhill near the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Chr. Feake.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  chi¹ B-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 28".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Origin --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GENEALOGIE OF CHRISTIANITY AND OF CHRISTIANS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DECLARED</hi> In a Sermon at Mercers Chappel before the Right Honourable the Lord Maior of the City of <hi>LONDON, April</hi> 28. 1650</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now thus publiſhed</hi> For the undeceiving of thoſe, who ſay they are <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and are not, but do lie; and for the Eſtabliſhment and Encouragement of thoſe, who having named the Name of <hi>Christ,</hi> do indeed depart (even in this hour of Apoſtacy) from all <hi>Iniquity,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> C. F. <hi>one of the Servants of the Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in the Miniſtery of the new Testament.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <bibl>
                     <hi>Anonym.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Christus non quaerit, utrum adhaereas huic vel illi nationali Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae: ſed utrum a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haereas verae fidaei, non utrum ſis Romanenſis, (Anglicanus Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſed utrum ſis vere ſanctificatus et renovatus.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Daven.</hi> in <hi>Coloſs.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> ver. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Peter Cole,</hi> at the Printing-Preſs in Cornhill near the Royal <hi>Exchange,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>THOMAS FOOT,</hi> Lord Major of this famous City of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow far the Great Antichrist, and degenerate Church of Rome have eclipſed, and thereby obſcured the originall glory of true Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, is beſt known to that rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of overcomming Christians in this Age, who are worthy in Chriſt his account, to walk with him in white. Aſsuredly Chriſtendome (as it is called for diſtinction ſake) is ſunck into ſo low a degree of degeneracy, as that in reſpect of Idolatry and Prophanneſſe, of impiety and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity, the Catholicks and Proteſtants alſo, for the moſt part, do ſo walk, as if it were their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died deſign, to render themſelves utterly unlike to Ieſus Chriſt; and unto this kind of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, he will profeſs at the laſt day. <hi>I never knew you, depart from me ye workers of iniquity!</hi> Oh therefore, how doth it concern the faithfull Diſciples of Ieſus Christ, to bring forth the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of the Genealogie of the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to emblazon according to the rules of Goſpel Heraldry, the native honour of this thrice noble Family, and that by an ornamental
<pb facs="tcp:114659:3"/>carriage and Converſation. But alas! how few do make it their holy ambition, to diſplay before the world the glorious Excellency of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, by acting in the life and power of this New-Teſtament unction?
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uc. 1.17.</note> It was Propheſied of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> that he ſhould go before the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> in the power and ſpirit of <hi>Elias,</hi> but it is the honour of the Saints, now in theſe times of the Goſpell, to go in and out, to do and to ſuffer in the power &amp; ſpirit of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> or Christ himſelf, &amp; may the number of ſuch Chriſtians be multiplied exceedingly: &amp; may the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that act &amp; walk in the power &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Antichriſt, of the Dragon, of the Beaſt, of the falſe-Prophet decreaſe abundantly;
<note place="margin">Rev: 16.13:</note> may the Generation of Renegadoes and Back-ſliders, of ſelf-condemned Hereticks, and Apoſtatized Profeſsours, who put the Son of God to an open ſhame, that ſpeak ſcornfully of the Word, the Spirit, the ways, the Ordnances of Ieſus Chriſt, may they, every one, be ſnared and taken, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented and fruſtrated in al their un-Chriſtian Ends, and means tending thereunto, may they never proſper in any of their Aſſemblies, Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings, Exhortations, which are of any tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the diſparagement of the wholeſome words, even the words of our Lord Ieſus Christ,
<note place="margin">1 Tim: 6:3, 4.</note> and the doctrine which is according to Godlineſse, and let all the Diſciples of Christ, all ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord, what thoughts of heart have been occaſioned by your Honours Commandement, and mine engagement, for the printing of the
<pb facs="tcp:114659:3"/>enſuing Sermon, is beſt known to the Author of ſo imperſect and unpoliſhed a Diſcourſe upon ſuch a weighty Theme. There was always an utter averſeneſse in my naturall Genius, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear on the Stage upon this account.
<note place="margin">John 7.4.</note> And I can ſay, through grace, I have never ſought to he known openly, or to ſhew my ſelf to the world, as being conſcious to a great unſitneſſe of Ingeny, and to the want of Spirituall Dexterity, for any work of this nature. But ſince it is your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips pleaſure, that this Sermon ſhould be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched over again in this <hi>other form,</hi> behold, (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tedious attendance for diſpatch, upon the proper instruments of this kind of publication) I humbly preſent it before your Honour, this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time; with ſome few convenient clauſes, here and there ſuperadded, beſeeching God, (who hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and the weak things of the world to confound the things that are mighty,) to command a Bleſſing upon theſe weak endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, wherein I did, and do aim at the <hi>new-Chriſtianizing</hi> of ſuch nominal Christians, as are really without God, and without Chriſt, dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, and I would to God, that all that heard me that day, were both almost and altogether Chriſtians, yea Christians upon the beſt account, ſo, as to be found unto great praiſe and honour and glory at the appearing of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips to command in the ſervice of the Goſpel. CHR. FEAKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 11.26. The laſt clauſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the Diſciples were called Chriſtians first in <hi>Antioch.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Iſtory and Prophecy are the Alpha and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega of the holy Scriptures and theſe two (the <hi>Knowledge of things paſt</hi> from the beginning of the world,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge of things to come,</hi> until the ending of time <hi>(et adhuc)</hi> and beyond) are the <hi>great deſire</hi> and <hi>delight</hi> of the <hi>intellectual world;</hi> All the ſons of men naturally thirſting after nothing more than <hi>this kind of knowledge,</hi> yea, even the <hi>excellency</hi> and <hi>perfection thereof.</hi> Now there are none other writings ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the world, worthy to be compared with the word of God, in reſpect of theſe two: For firſt, if you take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of <hi>Scripture Hiſtory,</hi> it takes the crown of glory from off the head of all other Hiſtories, for <hi>verity and antiquity;</hi> all other Records are of a later date, and have not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and the glory of <hi>Truth infallible</hi> ſtamped on them. Then ſecondly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praedictiones aliae ſuum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum habent, ſpiritustamen vaticinia, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</hi> Calv.</note> if you conſider <hi>Scripture Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> all other predictions and prognoſtications, all the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that ever were in the world beſides, cannot be a paralel to theſe, for their <hi>certainty and ſufficiency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this book of the new Teſtament, it is an Hiſtory of divers evangelical tranſactions, undertaken and mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (and his Apoſtles) in the world, immediately after his death, reſurrection, and aſcention
<pb facs="tcp:114659:5"/>into glory, and the Church could not be well without it, as ye may clearly diſcern by its <hi>great uſefulneſſe</hi> in a true Goſpel reformation: Providence, I ſay, hath well provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this part of the Scripture, for the advantage of the Saints (eſpecially of thoſe Diſciples that come out of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,)
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Act. 8.39. Let him that readeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</note> wherein, when they <hi>read</hi> and <hi>understand,</hi> they may know in many particulars, <hi>how they ought to walk,</hi> and <hi>to pleaſe God,</hi> as the Diſciples and Churches here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>walked</hi> and <hi>pleaſed God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think it meet to give you a brief narrative of ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages (from the firſt Chapter unto this preſent Scripture) as will make up a proper, and a neceſſary manuduction un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the enſuing and intended doctrine.</p>
            <p>After the <hi>Aſcention</hi> of the <hi>man Chriſt Ieſus into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. i. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to ſit down on the <hi>right hand of the Majeſty on high,</hi> (as the Holy Ghoſt phraſeth it) there were about an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty men and women aſſembled together with one accord in one place, (Diſciples they are called) wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the miſſion of the holy ſpirit: Chriſt had foretold, or told them before, that unleſſe he went away, the <hi>Comforter</hi> would not come; now he being gone to the Father, and they (by virtue of his command) abiding at Jeruſalem, and waiting for the promiſe of the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>ſending and deſcending of the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold in the ſecond chapter, the Holy Ghoſt comes down ſuddenly in a moſt <hi>glorious miniſtration,</hi> that the like was never heard of in the world before, <hi>and ſate upon each of the Apostles, in the appearance of cloven tongues like as of fire,</hi> whereby they were enabled on a ſudden to ſpeak in other tongues as the ſpirit gave them utterance; ſo that the Jews and Proſelites out of every nation, there reckoned up,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (moſt part of the nations in the world, at leaſt, under the Roman Empire) heard them ſpeak in their own language or proper dialect, the wonderfull works of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking a few words, in the middeſt of an amazed and mocking multitude, the Lord did ſo proſper and bleſſe what he and the reſt ſpake, that about three thouſand ſouls
<pb facs="tcp:114659:5"/>gladly received the word, and were added to that firſt new. Teſtament-church. Afterward the multitude of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples increaſed exceedingly. But now Satan, <hi>the God of this world, who blindeth the minds of them which believe not, lest the light of the glorious Goſpel of Christ ſhould ſhine unto them,</hi> indeavoured what he could, to prevent the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of it by raiſing up a <hi>cruel perſecution againſt the Church:</hi> Hereupon the Church was ſcattered,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Faedum in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum verber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus lacero, fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tracco.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Haling, drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging men and women to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> all except the Apoſtles; ſo there was the firſt new-Teſtament-Church ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered: which was but lately gathered, but (by an over-ruling hand of providence) the ſcattering of that firſt Church, was the gathering of many; for ſome went one way, ſome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, and where ever they came, they were inſtant in preaching the word, preaching the Lord Jeſus, holding forth the doctrine of the Goſpel. <hi>Philip</hi> went down to <hi>Samaria,</hi> and there brought in aboundance of people to Jeſus Chriſt. In this interim, there were planted <hi>Churches</hi> throughout all <hi>Iudaea, Galile, and Samaria:</hi> And in this eleventh chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that we may make haſte to the words of the text, at ver. 19. you have an hiſtorical account of the glorious ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Goſpel in the <hi>more remote parts</hi> among the Gentiles. <hi>Now they that were ſcattered abroad, upon the perſecution that aroſe about</hi> Stephen, <hi>travailed as far as Phaenice, and Cyprus, and Antioch, preaching the word to none but the Iews onely.</hi> They thought they alone were the people ro whom the glad tidings of the Meſſiah ſhould be publiſhed and proclaimed; but now at this Antioch, the hand of the Lord was ſo with them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Calvin <hi>in locum.</hi>
               </note> that a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Graecians</hi> believed and turned to the Lord.</p>
            <p>This being reported to the Church which was in Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, (for the Apoſtles being at Jeruſalem, had oportunity of bringing in others to the obedience of the faith, in ſtead of the diſperſed Diſciples) it was matter of great joy, and and they ſent forth <hi>Barnabas</hi> that he ſhould go as far as Antioch.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Civitas ab An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocho magno, denominata.</hi> Lyr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Antioch it bare the name of one of the Kings of Syria, one of them was a bitter enemie of the Church of the Jews, <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes;</hi> and for his rage and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they changed <hi>Epiphanes</hi> into <hi>Epimanes;</hi> and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Antiochus the Illuſtrious,</hi> they called him <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus
<pb facs="tcp:114659:6"/>the * furious.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Or <hi>Antiochus</hi> the mad.</note> In this <hi>City, Antioch,</hi> as formerly in <hi>Samaria, two eminent thrones of Satan,</hi> the Goſpel won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully prevailed, and was readily imbraced by a great number, much people was added to the Lord; <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> come hither, aſsemble themſelves with the Church a whole year, and teach much people. And now when Chriſt had <hi>Diſciples</hi> among the Jews, and <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> among the Gentiles; when he had a <hi>Church at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,
<note place="margin">That is, A. Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints called out of the world by the word, to the fellowſhip of the Goſpel.</note> Churches in Iudea, Galile, and Samaria, * a Church at Antioch,</hi> being a very conſiderable number of people, diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of the children of men, having Laws and Ordinances, ways of Worſhip differing from all other: they are called by a new diſtinguiſhing name, they are called Chriſtians. <hi>And the Diſciples were called Chriſtians first at Antioch:</hi> that was the firſt place where they received this appellation, and from thence the other Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, who hitherto were called Saints,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſtinctio vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eis ambiguae primum ſit in omni rerum conſideratione.</hi> Kec. Who is as the wiſe man? and who knoweth the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a thing? Eccl. 8.1.</note> Diſciples, and Diſciples of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Continuance of time hath rendred this word, a very ambiguous word, I mean the word <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this being the time of reformation, I ſpeak not of carnal external reformation, but of a reformation intended by Chriſt and his Spirit, we muſt indeavour to reform, not onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and things, but the names of things: and indeed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of this nature, is nothing elſe, but a <hi>Reduction of perſons and things, and names, to their original cauſes, in their firſt constitution, to form them again, as it were;</hi> which cannot be underſtood without <hi>explication</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction,</hi> as the rule of the School is: yea, that maxim in al the Schools of Philoſophie, and Theologie is moſt true &amp; uſeful, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Planto in</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that man which would teach aright, muſt firſt of all make a diligent enquiry into the names of things, whereby they are called, leſt being miſcalled or miſnamed; there be a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſion or a miſunderſtanding of things themſelves. so then this is the truth which I ſhall from theſe words re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend unto this audience this day, and I deſire it may take hold upon all your hearts, not onely in the <hi>explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it,</hi> but <hi>application</hi> alſo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:6"/>
            <p>The name, or title, or appellation, CHRISTIANS, was given originally, unto the <hi>Diſciples of Ieſus Christ.</hi> I mean Diſciples excluſively, and incluſively, excluding all others, including all ſuch.</p>
            <p>Now it is ſomewhat dark, as from the preſent Hiſtory,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt nominum impoſitio alia</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> how this name or appellation was given, whether <hi>occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> and accidentally; or <hi>from deliberation, by election and choiſe,</hi> as they uſually diſtinguiſh in this point. If upon conſideration, whether by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> or whether by <hi>the people of Antioch that were without,</hi> diſcerning this people in their doctrine and practiſe, to exalt the name and honour of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt onely and altogether; Or whether it was given by their <hi>enemies, by way of reproach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">As they were called alſo Nazarens.</note> calling them <hi>Chriſtians</hi> after the name of Chriſt, in a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ignominious manner; Or laſtly, whether it were impoſed by the <hi>ſpecial direction of the Spirit,</hi> this is not eaſily determined here by a negligent Reader, although it be a truth moſt evident, that this name was given at the firſt to the <hi>Diſciples of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet other Scriptures will help us in this thing, nay, I cannot but bring this verſe under trial, in order to the finding out of the true ground of the impoſition of this name upon the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt; for,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whereas it is in the tranſlation rendred paſlively, (they were called) and ſo no account is given by whom they were ſo called or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; if you render it actively, (the text will bear it) ſo a clear account is given of the nomenclators, who they were <hi>viz. Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas;</hi> for thus it may be read, And it came to paſſe, that they aſſembled together with the Church a whole year, and that they taught much people, or a great multitude, and <hi>that, they called or named the Diſciples, Chriſtians, firſt in Antioch.</hi> But if the moſt skilfull in this language, will contend for the paſſive conſtruction of the verb, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Kings tranſlators verſion, I ſhall not further intermeddle, though much may be ſaid (I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi>) in this dubious caſe, concerning the two firſt words of this verſe, in reference to the laſt clauſe;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:114659:7"/>but, as I ſaid, let it ſuffice, that there are other texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which do ſignificantly enough, expreſſe the divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of this title, as here, its at the firſt impoſed; as in 1 Pet. 4.16. he had ſaid in the 14. verſe, <hi>Jf ye be reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the name of Chriſt, happy are ye,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>But let none of you</hi> (Saints, Diſciples) <hi>ſuffer as a murtherer, or as a thief, or as an evil doer, or as a buſie bodie; yet if any ſuffer as a Chriſtian, let him not be aſhamed,</hi> (neither of the name, nor of the ſufferings, or puniſhments,) <hi>but let him glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God on this behalf.</hi> So that you ſee plainly, the Holy Ghoſt owneth this name, however it might be given at the firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vox ſit propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, determinata, et adae quata rei ſignifican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae, brevis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, ſed tres vocis magnas virtutes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectitur.</hi> Keck. <hi>log. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Pontificii non parum offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt doctrinae de Eccleſia et ejus membris, cum vocem (Clerus) quam Ap. Petrus tribuit omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fidelibus Christi mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris, quadam arrogantia te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meraria, ad turbam Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotum restrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntet ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulorum quaſi illi ſoli ſint ſors illa et hareditas Domini at que idcirco reliquae Chriſti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>embra quodnm ſupercilioſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectu vocant Laicos.</hi>
               </note> or by whomſoever, it being a name or title very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and very ſignificant, a word adaequate to the perſons named, and intended in that name; why, therefore it is to be accepted as given of God to the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt; yea, and this precious truth, this noble appellation, is not to be parted with eaſily, by the ſaints; they may ſafely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate it to themſelves, the whole, and the onely family of Jeſus Chriſt; to any other ſort of men beſides, how clamourous ſoever in their claims, it doth not appertain. As in a like caſe, both in the Catholick Church of Rome, and the national Church of England (as from cuſtome, and by tradition, and not from Scripture, they do call it,) the Prieſts, the Prelates, and their Curates do aſſume and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate to themſelves onely, the word Clergy, the Lords lot, or inheritance; calling the ordinary people, the Laity, and and the beſt of them lay-Elders, themſelves Divines, the Clergy, yea, the Church; whereas in the word of truth, the Saints, all of them, great and ſmall are the Lords Clergy, the Church,
<note n="*" place="margin">1 pet. 5 3.2 Pet. 1.4.</note> partakers of the Divine nature; and therefore how neceſſary is it, to <hi>reform</hi> and <hi>rectifie</hi> the very <hi>names,</hi> and <hi>titles</hi> of things and perſons, leſt otherwiſe the ſtrangers intermeddle with the childrens joy, and that <hi>worthy name</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, whereby they are of right <hi>named,</hi> and diſtinguiſhed, ſhould through their <hi>ignorance, filence,</hi> and <hi>negligence,</hi> come to be more and more <hi>blaſphemed</hi> and abuſed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:7"/>
            <p>Now for the managing of <hi>this truth</hi> for the beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, I ſhall firſt proceed to the <hi>removal</hi> of all thoſe which walk in any degree of contrariety thereunto, from having any part or fellowſhip in the dignity of this <hi>honourable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation,</hi> (ſo far as in me is,) and that is <hi>by way of nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> peremptorily denying thoſe to be juſtly or properly called <hi>Christians,</hi> who indeed are not ſuch, upon the terms mentioned in the text, viſibly Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall inſiſt upon the true <hi>notation</hi> of the word, <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and then give, by way of affirmation, the honour of that title to whom the honour thereof is due.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall be ready to give an account, what <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity in reaſon,</hi> what rational ground there is from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and otherwiſe, to <hi>enervate,</hi> nay to <hi>make void</hi> the <hi>title</hi> of <hi>meer pretenders</hi> and <hi>uſurpers;</hi> and in the authority and power of divine truth, to put the <hi>Diſciples of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in poſſeſſion of that <hi>honourable prerogative</hi> which of right belongs unto them. And <hi>theſe three things</hi> I am the more carefull to fix upon; becauſe, as in all other writings and diſcourſes we muſt neceſsarily put a difference between an <hi>abuſive word or phraſe,</hi> and a <hi>proper expreſſion:</hi> So here we muſt keep cloſe to the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>ſound words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and not call or account any man a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that is not a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in deed and truth,</hi> that was never yet a Diſciple of Jeſus Chriſt, no not by night, and ſecretly for fear of the Jews, as <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> it is to commit an <hi>abuſe</hi> in ſpeaking;
<note place="margin">Vocabula ſunt propria, cum his ipſis rebus ſignificandis adhibentur, propter quas ſunt inſtituta, huic virtuti <hi>opponitur</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>magna obſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis, ſaepe etiam erroris cauſa</hi>
               </note> it is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which hath been of very evil conſequence in this matter for many generations, as afterward you will well perceive.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe I ſhall ſpeak to in the <hi>general,</hi> and in <hi>particular;</hi> therefore in the <hi>general</hi> conſider, that the worſt and unworthieſt men have aſsumed to themſelves, and dignified themſelves with the moſt glorious Titles and Names that have been current among the ſons of men. The <hi>Turks</hi> at this day call themſelves <hi>Muſſlemans;</hi> i.e. <hi>right beleevers;</hi> and all the world beſides, are miſtaken in their Faith, if you beleeve themſelves concerning themſelves.
<pb facs="tcp:114659:8"/>The <hi>Papiſts</hi> they aſsume to themſelves the name of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> &amp; <hi>Christians,</hi> and they are the true <hi>Apostolick Church,</hi> and dignifie themſelves with all the glorious titles of this nature, that are abroad in the world; why now on the contrary, thoſe that have had moſt right to this <hi>illustri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous title of Chriſtians,</hi> and the like, they have been robbed, and diſrobed of their ornaments and garments in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect;
<note place="margin">If they have called the Maſter of the houſe Beelze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub, how much more them of of his houshold? Mat. 10.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> and in ſtead thereof, men have put upon them the moſt odious and hatefull names; <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, the <hi>head</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> was called a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and they ſaid he had a <hi>Devil; Paul</hi> a ring-leader of the <hi>ſect</hi> of the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> a ſeditious fellow, a very * <hi>peſt,</hi> as the word is; and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in this nation (as in the time of <hi>Popery rampant</hi>) the choiſeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and moſt precious of the people of God weie cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hereticks, Lollards;</hi> and of late days, in the time of the <hi>Prelaetes domination, Schiſmaticks, Puritans, Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and ſuch like terms of reproach they were branded withal. But now conſider what is to be ſaid in this firſt particular, the generality of men and women are not to be called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for from the beginning it was not ſo: thoſe that are not <hi>Chriſts Diſciples</hi> are not to be called and accounted <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> This is a time of reformation, juſtice, and right muſt be done to every one; by the authority of the word of God, I may pronounce ſentence againſt the far greateſt part of the people in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly and generally content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with taking Chriſts part in that which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, the name, and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, not caring for that which is anſwerable that is to die unto the word, and to live unto God <hi>Vald.</hi>
               </note> (as it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) who walk contrary to the <hi>example of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>practiſes of Christians,</hi> and the <hi>principles of Chriſtianity;</hi> they are degraded by the vertue of the truth in this word. <hi>The Diſciples, the Diſciples of Ieſus Christ,</hi> are to be called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and none other throughout the world.</p>
            <p>But more <hi>particularly.</hi> Firſt, Although the <hi>Papists,</hi> or <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> are called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinction to the <hi>Turks,</hi> the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> as you know, that are intelligent men in Hiſtories; yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, at the beſt, they are but <hi>Antichristian Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> nay indeed, they are <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> not <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for take the choiſeſt of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the moſt devout, and the moſt holy of the <hi>followers</hi> of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> why they are
<pb facs="tcp:114659:8"/>not <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> their doctrine is <hi>Babiloniſh</hi> doctrine for the moſt part, their devotion is <hi>Babiloniſh</hi> devotion,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> religious and honeſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Act. 13.50.</note> it is <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> holineſs, their worſhip, doctrine, tion favours not, hath not the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> no not the <hi>tincture</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> and if the <hi>devouteſt diſciples</hi> of the man of ſin, the <hi>tens</hi> and the <hi>hundreds</hi> of theſe, are not <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> much leſs their <hi>thouſand;</hi> and their <hi>millions</hi> of
<note n="*" place="margin">Natural bruit-beaſts. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 pet. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſenſual epicures,</hi> all theſe are cut off from any intereſt in this honour.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There are <hi>Vnchriſtian Chriſtians</hi> as well as <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian:</hi> theſe as they are not againſt Chriſt as thoſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned are againſt him, ſo neither are they with him, and
<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 12.30.</note> the words of Chriſt are, he that is not with me is againſt me, and I call them <hi>Vnchristian Chriſtians</hi> in a contra-diſtinction <hi>to the Antichrist and his diſciples,</hi> unto the Papiſts known uſually by another word, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the convention of ſome Princes of the Empire in Germany, at Smalcaldy, where in their writings to the Emperour they begin every head of their Articles with the word <hi>Proteſtamur, we protest,</hi> and from that time thoſe who did come off, and ſeparate from the Church of Rome, were called <hi>proteſtants,</hi> and that word and apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation paſt over the ſea into England, and ſo to other parts, they were afterwards ſub-divided into Lutherans, and Calviniſts;
<note place="margin">Proteſtant chriſtians, for the moſt part, not real chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, in Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> days cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts at large, and carnal Goſpellers.</note> Now the degenerate <hi>proteſtants</hi> of theſe times, becauſe they are not <hi>Antichristians,</hi> do eſteem and account themſelves our <hi>Orthodox Chriſtians,</hi> and yet the generality of them may be reputed <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Chriſtians,</hi> that is ſuch as have the title of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> undeſervedly, being altogether <hi>unlike</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt whoſe name they glory in, as if it did <hi>de jure</hi> belong unto them. And of theſe, two ſorts there are, firſt all <hi>looſe, lewd proteſtants:</hi> Secondly all <hi>formal, hypocritical profeſſours of Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt all <hi>licentious proteſtants,</hi> we muſt remove them from having any intereſt, in this title, by way of negation, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> they are not, though ſo they call themſelves, and aſsume (as if worthy thereof) the honour of this
<pb facs="tcp:114659:9"/>name; for as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaid of old concerning <hi>nominal Chriſtians</hi> of <hi>diſſolute converſation,</hi> that they are not <hi>men,</hi> in propriety of ſpeech, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo may I affirm of theſe <hi>Vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian proteſtants,</hi> their actions and tranſactions in the world ſavour not, reliſh not of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of a <hi>man,</hi> they are ſo brutiſh in their luſts, ſo filthy in their lives, the eldeſt <hi>ſons of Belial</hi> in their generation, and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count there will be diſcarded, and ſet by, many thouſands of people in this nation, men and women, high and low, rich and poor, Prieſts and people, that have the title and name of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> or <hi>proteſtants, baptiſed</hi> (as they ſay) into the <hi>name of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and yet do live more like unto Devils incarnate in all manner of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and licancſouſneſs, <hi>committing ſin with greedineſſe,</hi> than unto the firſt or <hi>primitive Christians,</hi> who were indeed the diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt
<note n="*" place="margin">If ye conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in my word, then are ye my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples indeed. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sed dicet ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis etiam de noſtris excede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quoſdam a regula diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinae: deſinunt tum ehriſtiani haberi penes nos.</hi> Tert. apo.</note>, who followed his doctrine and converſation, who <hi>obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine into which they were delivered.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly all <hi>formal profeſſours,</hi> that is, ſuch as make a <hi>plauſible ſhew,</hi> and carry it in their outward garb, as (not onely <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in name, but) <hi>Chriſtians</hi> upon the <hi>beſt account,
<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 9.1.</note> the diſciples of the Lord,</hi> and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding are no way worthy of that <hi>worthy name,</hi> for they are not <hi>Chriſtians inwardly</hi> in <hi>ſpirit</hi> and in <hi>power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but onely in
<note place="margin">o <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Gal 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>appearance,</hi> or <hi>face,</hi> or <hi>word,</hi> or <hi>letter</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5. Theſe diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>qui ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne diſtinguit, bene docet.</hi> Phil. 3.20.</note>, where Chriſt is at Gods right hand, but theſe men have not their converſation there, it is true they have not their converſarion in hell, (as it were) like the Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niake, among the graves, or <hi>apud inferos,</hi> as he alludes in the Comedy, nor have they their converſation in the world, upon ſo bad an account, in ſome ſence, as thoſe formerly mentioned, but they have their converſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>earth;</hi> betwixt <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>hell,</hi> as it were, as they paint Eraſmus, hanging betwixt both, for he was <hi>half</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and <hi>half</hi> a <hi>proteſtant,</hi> ſo all <hi>formal
<pb facs="tcp:114659:9"/>profeſſours</hi> they are but painted <hi>ſepulchres,</hi> they may be painted and pictured and drawn to the life (as meteors in the middle region of the air) hanging, living, converſing,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> luc. 12.30. live not in ſuſpence, be not as mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> tween <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpell,</hi> between <hi>works</hi> and <hi>grace,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Chriſt, &amp; Antichriſt,</hi> between <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or upon a ſuch like account, as this; they are like the <hi>Angel of the Church of Laodicea, they are neither hot nor cold, but lukewarm,</hi> partaking of both heat and cold, whom the Lord (as ſuch) will ſpew out of his mouth.</p>
            <p>Now leſt this <hi>diſtinction</hi> ſhould be <hi>offenſive</hi> to the <hi>formaliſts</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Scribes and Pharſees, * the formaliſts of thoſe times, were moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at Chriſt and his diſtinguiſhing doct. See Luc. 16.13, 14, 15.</note> (who do importunely aſsume to themſelves this honourable title, <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) as not being grounded upon ſcripture ſufficiently, I ſhall clear it from the language of the holy-Ghoſt, concerning the <hi>Iews</hi> in the old teſtament.</p>
            <p>For they were called <hi>Iews</hi> or <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> firſt in a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinction to the <hi>heathen nations,</hi> in all the world. A
<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 3.30.</note> 
               <hi>Jew</hi> was fully and plainly diſtinguiſhed, from a <hi>Gentile,</hi> but now ſecondly among themſelves, there was alſo a diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion; there were <hi>falſe Jews, lying Jews,</hi> as in the 2d. and 3d. of the Revelations, the Lord there ſpeaks of <hi>thoſe that ſay they are Jews, and are not, but do lie,</hi> and there were the <hi>true Iſraelites in whom is no guile; for all are not Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael that are of Iſrael,</hi> all are not the <hi>ſeed</hi> that are <hi>counted</hi> for the <hi>ſeed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 ſam 2.12.13, &amp;c.</note> therefore as you may ſee in the old teſtament among the Jews, <hi>ſome</hi> were <hi>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Belial,</hi> as the ſons of Eli, they were Jews, and in the Prieſts office, they drew near to the Lord, to the tabernacle of the Lord in Shiloh, yet were ſome of the moſt vile of the children of men,
<note n="*" place="margin">And <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> c. 1. called the Rulers of the Jews, Rulers of <hi>sodom:</hi> now the men of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odom</hi> were wic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and ſinners before the Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, Gen. 13.13.</note> (for they lay with the women that aſsembled at the door of the Tabernacle, and they ſent their ſervants to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the fleſh as it was ſeething, out of the Caldron by force and violence, and ſo abuſed and prophaned the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Lord:) And <hi>others</hi> were <hi>outwardly,</hi> and <hi>ſeemingly holy,</hi> and <hi>unblameable,</hi> like the Phariſees and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> before his converſion, unreproveable, touching the righteouſneſs which is of the Law, yet they are called hypocrites again and again, woe unto you Scribes
<pb facs="tcp:114659:10"/>and Phariſees,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.14</note> Hypocrites, even ſeven times, * in that chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: So now upon the like account in the times of the new-Teſtament thoſe that are called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from thoſe that are ſuch indeed and truth; for though <hi>hypocriticall profeſſours</hi> aſsume to themſelves that title, which is equivalent to the name of a <hi>true Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite,</hi> an <hi>Iſraelite in whom is no guile,</hi> viz. <hi>A Chriſtian,</hi> yet it is not to be permitted, for a very vaſt difference there is, between the one and the other; inſomuch, that I may with little alteration; apply the words of Chriſt unto theſe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 23.27, 28.</note> we are now ſpeaking of, * <hi>Woe unto ye formall profeſſours, hypocrites, for ye are like unto whited ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, which indeed appear beautifull outwardly, but within are full of dead mens bones, and of all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, even ſo ye alſo, appear righteous</hi> [Chriſtians] <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, but within ye are full of hypocriſie and iniquity.</hi> Thus you ſee to whom the <hi>title</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may juſtly be <hi>denied,</hi> they having <hi>no interest</hi> in this <hi>worthy name,</hi> whereby the <hi>Diſciples of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> are <hi>dignified</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſhed;</hi> but if notwithſtanding this that hath been ſpoken, they will account it a kind of robbery to be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of what they have ſo long poſseſsed, (for many make a profeſſion of Chriſtianity, richly plauſible) let it be agreed, call them Chriſtians, but with this proviſo that they admit an Epithere ſuitable, and proper for them, <hi>falſe, falſe-Chriſtians,</hi> and then ſure I am, their honour for which they ſo contend, will nevertheleſſe be laid in the duſt, as of old,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2. 2 Cor. 11.13. Gal. 2.4.</note> * <hi>falſe-Prophets, falſe-Apoſtles, falſe, Teachers, falſe-Brethren,</hi> ſo now, <hi>falſe-Christians, falſe-Diſciples,</hi> will not this be a more ſtigmaticall brand upon them, than the ſingle deniall of that forementioned appellation can amount unto? And this may be ſufficient for the <hi>firſt</hi> viz. <hi>The extinguiſhing the title</hi> of the ſeverall <hi>uſurpers</hi> and <hi>pretenders,</hi> who claim an intereſt in this <hi>name of Goſpel honour,</hi> as if of the ſame houſe and ſtock, with theſe here ſpoken, of in the text. <hi>And the Diſciples were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:10"/>
            <p>In the next place we come to conſider the <hi>notation</hi> of <hi>the word; Chriſtian</hi> is derived from <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>word</hi> is a <hi>word of the</hi> Greek language, ſignifying anointed ones, <hi>Chriſt being the chief anointed one,</hi> and they his <hi>fellows,</hi> with this difference, <hi>he is anointed with the oil of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe above his fellows,</hi> that as in the powring the oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon <hi>Aarons</hi> head; the head being the principall part of the body, did firſt of all receive the ointment, and from thence it came down to the skirts of his cloathing, and all his garments ſavoured of the ſweet ointment made by Gods appointment, in the 30. of <hi>Exodus</hi> and the 23. ſo now, the <hi>Goſpel anointing,</hi> was powred firſt upon Jeſus Chriſt; as our Head, the Head of all beleevers, and from him, the Head, it did, and doth deſcend and flow down, even to the very skirts of his garments, the <hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> and <hi>loweſt Saint</hi> in all the world; and it is his due to have this appellation, this title of dignity and diſtinction from the reſt of the children of men
<note n="*" place="margin">but ye have an unction from the holy One. 1 Joh. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>the anointed of God, the anointed of God,</hi> as Jeſus Chriſt was anointed, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is called the <hi>Anointed One,</hi> and they may be called from him the <hi>anointed ones;</hi> for as the two words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Gramaticall derivation do both grow upon the ſelf-ſame root <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but with this diſtinction among others, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a degree near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the root then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo the <hi>two perſons</hi> ſignified by theſe <hi>two words</hi> viz. <hi>Chriſt</hi> and a <hi>Christian,</hi> in the new-Teſtament ſence, do both partake of the ſelf ſame <hi>unction,</hi> with this difference, that every <hi>Chirſtian</hi> is more remote from the <hi>fountain</hi> of <hi>unction</hi> then Chriſt is, he receiving it
<note n="*" place="margin">immediates.</note> immediately, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> receives what he receives, by
<note n="*" place="margin">mediante chriſto.</note> means of <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> firſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> afterwards they that are <hi>Chriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word Chriſt is alſo expreſſed in the old-Teſtament, by a word proper to that language, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> now the ſelf ſame word that is attributed to chriſt, sgiven to others beſides him, (indeed it belongs unto him <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently</hi> and <hi>emphatically, the Meſſiah.</hi> John 1.41.
<note place="margin">Joh. 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>we have found the Meſſiah which is, being interpreted, the Christ;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114659:11"/>and the Tranſlators read <hi>Daniel</hi> 9.25. <hi>the Meſſiah</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Although there be <hi>no,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>emp haticum</hi> prefixed, to either word.</note> the Prince) as in the 105. Pſal there you ſhall find plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the holy Ghoſt doth not ſpeak of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> yet thoſe there ſpecified, are called by that name, <hi>touch not mine anointed, and do my Prophets no harm,</hi> verſe 15. Touch not my Chriſts, <note place="margin">Pſalm. 105.<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> mine anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. pſalm.<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> his anointed.</note> my <hi>Meſſiahs,</hi> the ſame word that is in the ſecond Pſalm, his anointed, his Chriſt, as it is interpreted by <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 4. v. 26.27. And before I paſſe from hence, you may underſtand, this <hi>anointing</hi> is no other thing, then the <hi>anointing</hi> of the <hi>Spirit. The Spirit of the Lord God is upon me, becauſe the Lord hath anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to Preach,</hi> &amp;c. as you read in the 61 of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the firſt ver. ſo there is the notation of the word <hi>Christian</hi> gramatically.</p>
            <p>But now <hi>thirdly,</hi> You muſt obſerve the word, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it hath <hi>congruity of reaſon,</hi> in its logical notation: Chriſtians ſo called from Chriſt, they have this <hi>denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> in <hi>congruity</hi> of <hi>reaſon</hi> upon a four-fold account, or in four reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of <hi>doctrine.</hi> 2. in reſpect of <hi>converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 3. in reſpect of <hi>intereſt.</hi> 4. in reſpect of <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Christians</hi> are ſo called from Jeſus Chriſt upon this account, of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Grammatica nudam vocem, non naturam conſiderat</hi> Gr. log.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Logicus vocem conſiderat, non qua vox, ſed qua ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>entis intelligentiam refertur, et rem explicat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Keker. in log.</p>
               </note> reaſon, becauſe they (and they onely) do underſtand, receive, and embrace <hi>the truth as it is in Ieſus,</hi> and no other ſort of people in the world do the like,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non ſonum ſolum nominis expectes, ſed et ſenſum.</hi> Tert. <hi>Receperunt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minari Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani a Chriſto, ſicut Platonici a Platone. Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> in <hi>locum.</hi>
               </note> this is one <hi>diſtinguiſhing Character;</hi> every Maſter, or Rabbi, or Teacher, hath had his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to any <hi>eminency,</hi> in any new and ſingular kind of <hi>learning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were among the heathens of old, about Chriſts time and before, the diſciples of <hi>Plato,</hi> the diſciples of <hi>Ariſtotle, Aristotelians,</hi> and <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> ſo diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, becauſe that the one followed the doctrines, and teachings of <hi>Plato,</hi> others followed <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for truth what he taught them, there were diſciples that were called Epicurians of <hi>Epicurus</hi> the Philoſopher, others were Stoicks, the Diſciples of that Doctrine, as the
<pb facs="tcp:114659:11"/>Holy-Ghoſt gives you to underſtand, Acts. 17.18. but its no way neceſſary to acquaint this audience, with the ſeverall particular doctrines and oplnions of theſe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi> Only thus, to our preſent purpoſe every one of theſe <hi>Masters</hi> of <hi>learning;</hi> they had their Diſciples, and their diſciple-ſhip conſiſted in this, in owning and cleaving to the doctrines, and opinions of their Teachers, as they were doctrines diſtinct from all other doctrines in the world, upon all occaſions letting the world know, by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes and profeſſions, by whoſe name they had choſen to be known and diſtinguiſhed from other men. Now (as I ſaid) <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in like manner, derive their name, as other diſciples, from their great Doctour, the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in reſpect of the <hi>particular distinct doctrine of the Goſpel</hi> (learned from him and that in a ſingular manner) differing from all other doctrines in the world:
<note place="margin">John 9 28. VVe are Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes diſciples. Mar. 2.18. The diſciples of John and of the Phariſees diſtinguiſhed from Chriſts diſciples.</note> They cannot be called <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Diſciples</hi> *, neither can they be called <hi>Iohns Diſciples,</hi> neither can they be called the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> (conſidered as in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of innocency, as they ſpeak) in reſpect of their own righteouſneſs; but they are the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they own, and cleave to the pure, proper Evangelical truth, thoſe divine, ſupernatural truths, which are <hi>reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by the <hi>Son</hi> from the <hi>boſome</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adam</hi> in his <hi>first estate,</hi> nor the children of men ſince that time, have been able, by ſtrength of <hi>rational en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries,</hi> to find out, underſtand, and entertain; yea ſuch truths, as the holy Angels themſelves were not aware of,
<note place="margin">Iuc 1.31, &amp;c. John 1.14. 1 Tim. 3.16. Epheſ. 1.4. Rom. 3.28. Gal. 2.20. Rom: 8:11: Heb: 7:25:26</note> until revealed, <hi>viz. In the beginning was the word, and the word was with God, and the word was God.</hi> Joh. 1.1. <hi>And the word was made fleſh. And great is the myſtery of godlineſſe (Chriſtian godlineſſe) God was manifeſted in the fleſh;</hi> and the reſt of the doctrine of the <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Again, <hi>Election in Chriſt before the world began. Iuſtification by faith without the works of the law. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by the faith of the Son of God. The i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dwelling of the Spirit in the hearts of beleevers. The ſending of the Spirit from the Father and the Son, The man Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.
<pb facs="tcp:114659:12"/>The doctrine of Chriſts interceſſion at the right hand of the Majeſty on high,</hi> and that in our nature. With many other glorious Goſpel truths, which the Angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to look into; thus you may ſee what I intend by the doctrine of Chriſt, as diſtinct from all other doctrines. And ſurely thoſe that are ignorant of theſe and other Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel truths, ſtrangers to this <hi>divine learning,</hi> cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called <hi>Christians.</hi> Indeed Antichriſt and his diſciples, pretend to be Chriſtians, and diſciples of Chriſt, as you heard, and its true, ſome of theſe doctrines fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned they profeſs to cleave unto, but that of 1 <hi>Titus</hi> is verified in them, <hi>they profeſſs that they know God but on works they deny him,</hi> &amp;c. And becauſe of the admix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of contrary doctrines, ſummed up in the confeſſion of faith, made at the Councell of Trent, their doctrine may be called a <hi>mungrel doctrine,</hi> and ſo their worſhip, like that ſet up of old, by the <hi>Jewiſh-Prieſt,</hi> among the ſeveral nations, 2. Kings. 17.33.41. they ſerved the Gods of the lands and of the Countries, and they ſerved <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> there was a mixture in their doctrine and worſhip; and you know, what the learned writers and beſt ſchollers that contend againſt the Papacy, ſay of them, their doctrine and worſhip, their whole religion is a <hi>Miſcelany,</hi> made up <hi>partly,</hi> of the Jewiſh Doctrines and practiſes, and <hi>partly</hi> of the heatheniſh doctrine and practiſes, and <hi>partly</hi> of the doctrines and practiſes of Chriſtians, but that is the leaſt part, it being compoſed chiefly of Moſaicall and heatheniſh inſtitutions, unwritten traditions, and many ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous ceremonies: and the more any ſhall indeavour the introduction of thoſe doctrines which are not taught by the Lord Jeſus and his Apoſtles, the more improbable is it, they ſhould be eſteemed the diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt, and conſequently Chriſtians, at the laſt day, for as you ſee he that is a true Chriſtian, underſtands <hi>the truth as it is in Ieſus,</hi> and receives it and cleaves unto it according to the
<note place="margin">a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mary ſate at Jeſus feet to hear his word, Luc. 10.39.</note> 
               <hi>meaſure of faith given unto him,</hi> and as the <hi>righteouſneſs of God is revealed from faith to faith,</hi> ſitting at Ieſus his feet to hear his word, as the manner of Diſciples was of old time,
<note place="margin">b <hi>Paul</hi> brought up at the feet of <hi>Gama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel,</hi> and taught, &amp;c. Acts 22:3.</note> and is unto this day.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:12"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are ſo called from <hi>Christ,</hi> in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity</hi> of <hi>reaſon</hi> in this reſpect, becauſe ſo ſoon as they are Chriſtians, there is ſuch a ſweet ſimilitude between. Chriſt and them, in point of converſation, that they mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and reciprocally reſemble each other, to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Angels and diſcerning men, where there is a <hi>great diſſimilitude</hi> betwixt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the children of men, there is wanting a <hi>ground</hi> in <hi>reaſon,</hi> to call ſuch men Chriſtians. As it is an utter abſurdity, to call the Jews or Turks or wicked perſons, <hi>Christians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no ſimilitude in them, becauſe utterly unlike to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, ſo on the other ſide where any are found, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving</hi> as <hi>Chriſt teacherh,</hi> and <hi>walking</hi> as he <hi>walked,</hi> obſerved <hi>to be in the world, as he was in the world,</hi> it is moſt proper to call and account ſuch as theſe are, Chriſtians and diſciples; and when beleevers grow up to <hi>eminency,</hi> in <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>practiſe,</hi> reflecting much of the glory of Chriſt upon the world in theſe two: Oh then how fitly may they receive this honourable appellation, <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Diſciples of the higheſt form, <hi>their Profiting appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto all.</hi> This part of their diſcipleſhip is properly called <hi>imitation,</hi> or <hi>following</hi> of the Lord. <hi>Be ye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of me as</hi> I <hi>am of Chriſt,</hi> the words are,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor. 11.1.</note> be ye imitators of me. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. and ſo 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came followers of us and of the Lord,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> imitators of us, and of the Lord. And ſaith <hi>Paul, thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ully known my doctrine, manner of life.</hi> In the margin of ſome of your Bibles, it is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Tim. 3.12.</note> thou haſt been a diligent follower of my manner of life. Now this <hi>imitating</hi> and <hi>following</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the manner of his life, conſiſts in theſe three particulars, firſt in <hi>being,</hi> ſecond in <hi>doing,</hi> third in <hi>ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> after the manner that Ieſus Chriſt, was, and did do and ſuffer in the world.
<note n="*" place="margin">A Chriſtians converſation in point of demeanour in the world is like Chriſts demeanour.</note> Firſt of all they are in the world, as Chriſt was in the world, not of it, while they are in it; you may know what was the frame and temper, and as I may ſo ſay, the <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vine Genius</hi> of the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt, in regard of his father, how he delighted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with God in prayer, and communion with him that
<pb facs="tcp:114659:13"/>way, by meditation and the like. And you know the genius and property, and the frame of the heart of Jeſus Chriſt towards his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that had received the ſame ſpirit, how much love and delight in their company, to teach them and to reveal to them the great things of God, that they might grow in grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You know his demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and carriage while he was in the world, to Publicans and ſinners, how he did reveal the love of God to them in the world, and tels them, that
<note n="*" place="margin">John 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever beleeveth on him ſhould not periſh but have everlasting life.</hi> And I am he that God the father hath appointed, and ſealed; and ſent into the world. He did not lift up his voice in the ſtreets, he was not tumultuous nor turbulent, but there was abundance of ſweetneſſe, meekneſſe, and gentleneſſe; thus he was in the world, and we ſhould be ſo in the world, and by how much the more, Chriſtians are like unto Jeſus Chriſt, by ſo much the leſſe, they are of the world, as it is in the 17th of <hi>Iohn,</hi> in the midſt of that chapter, twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated by Chriſt, to the father. <hi>Father</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they are not of the world, as</hi> I <hi>am not of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then ſecondly,
<note n="2" place="margin">In reſpect of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, their actions and tranſactions in the world, they are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt.</note> For their actings, Jeſus chriſt did not keep al his goodneſſe to himſelf while he lived, and make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the better for him when he died, as the cuſtome of rich men is, they will keep their eſtates cloſe while they live, and do little or no good
<note n="*" place="margin">That is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively or in any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity.</note> in the place of their abode they dy, there is a reſurrection of their eſtates, when they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves go down to the grave, then their eſtates ſhall riſe up in their ſtead, but oftentimes, it attains not the end which they propounded. But now from the time that Jeſus chriſt was anointed at his Baptiſm, and the holy Ghoſt came down upon him in the ſhape of a Dove, and a voice was heard, ſaying, <hi>This is my wel beloved ſon in whom</hi> I <hi>am wel pleaſed,</hi> which voice we heard ſaith <hi>Peter</hi>) from that time forth for three years and a half, the whole ſpace of his life,
<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 10.38.</note> 
               <hi>he went up and down doing good,</hi> preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdome, healing ſickneſſes, and performing all duties and offices that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed
<pb facs="tcp:114659:13"/>to him as he was the Son of Man, the <hi>Man Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> &amp; ſo ought <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in conformity to him, to have their converſation here in the world, to be willing to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, ready to communicate,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtianns popullus per omnia ſanctus eſt, et non in templis tantum et ritibus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiasticis ſed in omni vita, omnitempore, omnibus in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus omnibus factis ac studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is, nomins &amp; gloriae Chriſti conſecratus,</hi> Muſc.</note> to order their whole converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aright, doing what the wil of the Lord is as Chriſt ſaid <hi>I come to do thy will, O God,</hi> and ſo to be imitators or followers of him, not onely in <hi>outward demeanour,</hi> and <hi>behaviour</hi> (which yet is exceeding comely and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, <hi>viz.</hi> to be in behaviour, as it becommeth Saints) but alſo more eſpecially, in our <hi>actions, practiſes,</hi> and <hi>whole courſe of life.</hi> And moreover obſerve,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Luc. 12.13</note> When one ſaid unto Jeſus Chriſt, Speak to my Brother, that he divide the inheritance with me, he would not intermeddle in the matter which belonged not to him, but anſwered, <hi>Man, who made me a Iudge, or a Divider among you?</hi> He would not be a Buſie-body
<note n="(b)" place="margin">He was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of ſouls, 1 Pet. 2. ult. but not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, A buſie body Biſhop. The ambitious Clergy of all ages have been notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the contrary witneſs the Hiſtories of the ſeveral Kingdomes round about.</note> in other mens matters. In this thing, all true <hi>Christians</hi> ſhould approve themſelves his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> treading in this very foot-ſtep. Oh take heed of ſtretching your ſelves beyond your line; keep within your compaſſe; ſhine as bright as you may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your own Orbs; move with as much advantage to the world, in your proper Sphears, as is poſſible: ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as interpoſe, and intrude into anothers Province, are utterly unlike to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And then <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in point of <hi>Suffering,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was brought before Authority, he did not reproach and vilifie them, but with <hi>meekneſſe of wiſdome,</hi> or mock wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſpake to <hi>Pilate</hi> concerning truth, and other matters that paſſed between them; when he was reviled he reviled not again; when he ſuffered, he threatened not, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf to him that judgeth righteouſly, and ſaith the Apoſtle, he hath left us an
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Leaving a written copy. And Diſciples ought to write after their Maſters copy</note> 
               <hi>Example,</hi> that we ſhould tread in his ſteps. And truly in all Ages, <hi>Genuine Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> have made it a principal part of their care, to approve themſelves the diciples of the Lord Jeſus in this particular.</p>
            <p>Now in the <hi>Third</hi> place, <hi>Christians</hi> are denominated from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe they promote his <hi>Intereſt;</hi> conſider therefore, what is the <hi>great Intereſt</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt in its
<pb facs="tcp:114659:14"/>ſeveral parts. Firſt of all, the glorifying the Father in the Son. Secondly, the glorifying himſelf with the Father. And Thirdly, the convincing the world of Sin, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and Judgement by the Spirit. This is part of the <hi>great Interest</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, that the world through him might be ſaved; Now if you are <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> upon the account mentioned in the <hi>Text,</hi> you will, as Diſciples of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> carry on his <hi>Intereſt;</hi> then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you eat or drink, or what ever you do, you will aim at the glory of God,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.11.</note> that God in all things may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed through Jeſus Chriſt. And again, if you are chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.23.</note> you will indeavour that the name of Chriſt may be magnifyed, and exalted alſo, as you deſire the Father may be magnified,
<note place="margin">Joh. 17.5.</note> and exalted, Joh. 13.31, 32.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe, It concerns chriſt nearly, and it is a <hi>great part</hi> of his <hi>Intereſt,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.23.</note> That the world might know that the Father hath ſent him,</hi> and that they might know the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randupon which he is ſent, the ſaving of ſinners. Now every one of you, who are the Diſciples of chriſt of a truth, ſhould according to his Talent received, ſay and do, as the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> of himſelf and others,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.1, 2, 3</note> 
               <hi>That which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of life, That will we declare unto others, that they may have fellowſhip with us, and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> It is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Diſciples, true to their Maſter, to multiply their number, and gain in others: The Diſciples of Chriſt, chriſtians, have greater cauſe than any other, to purſue this part of their Maſters Intereſt, and an obligation lies upon them accordingly.</p>
            <p>Again, another part of chriſts <hi>Interest,</hi> which is very conducible to this honour, ſo far as it is advanced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, the
<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 110.1. Heb. 10.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, henceforth expecting till his foes be made his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oot ſtool.</note> 
               <hi>making all his foes his foot-ſtool,</hi> the bringing them all down, even under his feet. The <hi>preſent Intereſt</hi> of Chriſt is the Revealing and deſtroying of his Grand Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>The Autichriſt,</hi> and the ſubduing the Kings of the Earth, who have committed Fornication with the Whore
<pb facs="tcp:114659:14"/>of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who having one mind, give their power and ſtrength unto the beaſt, and make war with the Lamb.
<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13.2. The Dragon gave him his powet, or ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, his ſeat and great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>Vide</hi> Med. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> The intereſt of the beaſt is to maintain his power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given by the Dragon, even beyond the two and forty moneths allotted to him by divine appointment. The Man of ſin, the Son of perdition aſſumeth to himſelf, and accepteth from others, names and titles of honour and glory; Nay exalteth himſelf above all that is called God or worſhipped, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Openeth his mouth in blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt God to blaſpheme his name, at the ſame time gratifieth the Kings of the earth with magnificent titles, giving to the King of Spain the title of the moſt <hi>Catholick King,</hi> to the King of France the moſt <hi>Chriſtian King,</hi> to the King
<note n="*" place="margin">Henty 8th. <hi>Vid.</hi> Fox. <hi>Acts and Mon.</hi>
               </note> of England, (for <hi>helping the Papacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Luther.</hi>) <hi>Defendor of the faith,</hi> &amp;c. Now conſider it is the <hi>intereſt</hi> of Chriſt in this age, to obſcure and ſtain all this ſplendor and glory, by his ſhining forth in the greateſt glory, of that moſthonourable title, Lord of Lords, &amp; King of Kings, intended purpoſely for theſe times wherein we live. Now therefore, O all ye Chriſtians, that are indeed diſciples of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, awake, awake, the enemies of Chriſt are now to be made his foot-ſtool, purſue this intereſt to the utmoſt in your ſeveral places and callings, ſee to it that you beleeve and rceive a compleat victory over the Beaſt, and over his Image, and over his mark, and over the number of his name; ſee to it that you have not his mark either in your fore-heads, or in your right hands, for the Lamb ſhall overcome and they that are with him, called, and choſen, and faithfull. And this ſhall ſuffice for the 3 reaſon, why the Diſciples of Chriſt are called Chriſtians, becauſe after the manner of <hi>true diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> they promote the proper and ſeverall <hi>interests</hi> of their Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, and thoſe who are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded, cannot in good <hi>congruity</hi> of <hi>reaſon,</hi> be properly called or accounted chriſtians, look whoſe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt you moſt promote his diſciples indeed you are. Its a Noble Study ſeriouſly to enquire, what is the <hi>preſent great intereſt</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, and a great honour to all
<pb facs="tcp:114659:15"/>true Chriſtians to carry it on effectually.</p>
            <p>And then fourthly, and chiefly, though laſtly. Chriſtians were and are ſo called from Chriſt, in reſpect of the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude,</hi> nay I may ſay <hi>Identity</hi> of their <hi>Principles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what! though men profeſs to entertain and receive the truths of Chriſt, the pure &amp; Evangelical doctrine diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from all other doctrines &amp; truths, in the world? what though they ſhould profeſſe to have their converſation in heaven, in reſpect of holy duties, unblameable converſation and ſweet carriage in doing good, and in not being of the world, free in outward appearance from covetouſneſs, and covetous practiſes, and free from uncleanneſs, filthineſs, and fordidneſs of living; and what though they ſhould ſeem to join with the people of God, in carrying on the cauſe of God, and intereſt of Chriſt, againſt the common enemy; yet if they ſhould be and do all this, and much more then this, if they ſhould not do it from that principle which is proper to Chriſtians, but from a principle of violence from without, or a principle ſet on work, by virtue of an end, that is not ſuitable and congruous unto the great end that Chriſt propoundeth, then certainly all the glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of theſe men would lie in the duſt, notwithſtanding all the three former, and this is on purpoſe brought in, to ſpoil the claim and title of the beſt painted hypocrite, or falſe Chriſtian though acting in the moſt glorious garb, and carriage of himſelf.</p>
            <p>And therefore mark and conſider, what was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Jeſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Here ſome were obſerved to ſit and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eep.</note> from which he acted; (if any of you are ſleepy and drowſie, rouze up your ſelves for this is of great importance.) The principle by which Chriſt Jeſus had his being in the world, and acted, and ſuffered, and carried on the work that appertained to him, it was <hi>the ſpirit of God</hi> as you heard before, in the 61 of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the firſt. <hi>The ſpirit of the Lord is upon me and he hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed me,</hi> the ſpirit hath anointed me; nay, the ſpirit is that anointing, in the book of <hi>Exodus,</hi> a place formerly hinted you, There the compoſition of that holy anointing oil, which was to be poured upon the type of Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:114659:15"/>the high Prieſt <hi>Aaron,</hi> and upon his ſons, and upon all the holy veſsels and utenſils of the Tabernacle, is at large deſcribed, it is compounded of the richeſt ſpices, the moſt aromatical, the moſt odoriferous ſpices, together with the oil Olive an Hin, as it is there expreſsed in the 30. of <hi>Exodus</hi> the 23. &amp; 24. Thou ſhalt take to thee principall ſpices, of pure Myrrhe five hundred ſhekels, and of ſweet Cinamon, half ſo much, two hundred and fifty ſhekels, and of ſweet Calamus two hundred and fifty ſhekels, and of Caſsia five hundred ſhekels after the ſhekel of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and of the oil olive an Hin, and this ointment was to be madeafter the Art of the Apothecary, the ingredients to be exactly weighed, as the textſpeaks. And thou ſhaltant ointwith this ointment the Tabernacle, and the Ark, &amp; the veſsels, and thou ſhalt ſanctifie them, that they may be moſt holy, and thou ſhalt anoint <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſons and conſecrate them, that they may miniſter to me in the Prieſts office. Now this was but a Typical repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that holy anointing of Jeſus Chriſt by the ſpirit, and the anointing of his ſons, his people, his children, his diſciples after him.</p>
            <p>And in the Canticles, when Chriſt comes to look after his ſpouſe, comparing her to a garden, <hi>my ſiſter, my ſpouſe is a Well incloſed, a Fountain ſealed,</hi> &amp;c. thy plants are an Orchard of Pome-granates, with pleaſant fruits, with Camphire, &amp; Spicknard, &amp; Saffron, Calamus, Crynamon, Myrrhe &amp; Aloes, and the like. Now theſe ſpices of <hi>Arabia foelix,</hi> thoſe aromaticall ſpices in thoſe hot countries of the world, they are of a moſt pleaſant ſmell, and as Jeſus Chriſt was made pleaſant by the anointing of the holy Ghoſt, grace was poured into his lips, he ſpake as never man ſpake, and grace was poured into his whole conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, his whole carriage ſavoured of the ſweetneſs of the ſpirit of God. So if you are Chriſtians, you are anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſelf ſame ſpirit, if any here ſay they are <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, and have not the ſpirit of Chriſt,</hi> they are not <hi>Chriſtians, they are none of his Diſciples.</hi> For if they were of his Diſciples and Chriſtians, they have received
<pb facs="tcp:114659:16"/>of this anointing, it would run down from him the Head, upon the Officers of the church, and then upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, even to the door-keepers of the <hi>Churches of the Saints,</hi> the ointment will run upon theſe, and they ſhould ſmell of it in their converſation, whereever they did walk or ſpeak, ſweetneſs ſhould break forth at their lips, and it could not be but where ever they came, they would ſmell of that ſacred ointment too, of that holy anointing, and their actions, would ſavour of the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt. Now, this ſpirit, I ſhould inſiſt upon it, as being the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple indeed,</hi> as it is an <hi>informing Principle,</hi> as it is an <hi>actuating P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inciple,</hi> as it is an <hi>aſſesting Principle,</hi> and as it hath been and is <hi>in our ſpirits,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cting with <hi>Chriſts ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit,</hi> ſo that whatſoever we do as Chriſtians, we ſhould do, going forth in the ſtrength of that anointing. In the 1 Joh. 2. and the latter end, read it over. <hi>But that anointing which you have received of him, abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you of all things, and is truth, and is no l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; and even as it hath taugh you ye ſhall abide in him;</hi> which is a choice ſcripture, and none underſtand it (though they underſtand the Grammar of it, they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not the Theologie, the Divinity of it) but thoſe that have received it. For Chriſt in the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſpeaking of the Comforter, this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing, ſaith he,
<q rend="margQuotes">which or whom the world cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, for they know him not, but ye know him; for he ſhall abide or dwell and be in you for ever.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And this ſhal ſuffice now, for the doctrinal part, ſhewing you how in <hi>congruity of reaſon,</hi> the Diſciples of Chriſt are called Chriſtians, becauſe they ſavour and receive the <hi>doctrine</hi> of Chriſt, &amp; they are imitators of the <hi>Converſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion</hi> of Chriſt, they promote the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>Principles</hi> by which he acted, they likewiſe act in the world. And indeed a through conſideration of theſe 4 <hi>particulars,</hi> ſhould marvellouſly induce Chriſtians, to be ambitious to hold forth the glory and honour of that honourable title
<pb facs="tcp:114659:16"/>
               <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as becommeth the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Now in the next place, for <hi>application</hi> of this <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:</hi> the remainder of the time ſhall be ſpent that way. Is it ſo that this honourable title and name <hi>[Chriſtians]</hi> was given originally unto none but the <hi>Diſciples of Ieſus Christ,</hi> unto the Churches of Chriſt, <hi>of a new, Teſtament form and frame;</hi> as you may ſee in the words before the text. They aſſembled themſelves with the Church a whole year and taught much people and when they became a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of people, then they had a new name given them, the <hi>Diſcriples</hi> were called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> &amp;c. then firſt of all for <hi>Information and inſtruction</hi> of all thoſe in this Congregation, that are ignorant of this point. By this we may take a <hi>due eſtimate</hi> of the <hi>number</hi> of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> in the world, how many there may be in the world. Men heretofore (it may well be) have thought there haue been more Chriſtians in the world than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there were. And now its more than probable that divers here preſent will be more charitable and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable in their Computation of the number than they ought to be, leſt they ſhould exclude themſelves. This doctrine will help us to take an eſtimate of them, thus: By that time all thoſe whoſe <hi>Converſation</hi> is in Hell as it were, that make a Hell upon earth, all Divels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate you know ſuch there are, the unclean ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit worketh effectually in them, the Children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and yet are called Proteſtants, and called Chriſtians by that time I ſay theſe are abſtracted; By that time thoſe whoſe <hi>Converſation</hi> is upon earth, that are earthly minded men, that mind the world, and the things thereof; By that time I ſay theſe are diſcounted, by that time all thoſe, whoſe <hi>Converſation</hi> is between Heaven and Earth, as it were between God and Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, they are not down-right Altheiſts nor Papiſts, but Proteſtants, but yet carnall, or looſe, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> formall at beſt
<pb facs="tcp:114659:17"/>as being Chriſtians in an outward garb onely, by that time theſe are diſcarded and ſet aſide as utterly Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal: by that time, this is done, even in this Nation, how many, think you, will be left, concerning whom it may beſpoken, and that in truth, that they are Chriſtians, and Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Diogenes</hi> in his time, (he was a very notable Philoſopher, <hi>Alexander</hi> the great much admiring him, ſaying, if he had not been <hi>Alexander,</hi> he woud have been <hi>Diogenes</hi>) when he ſaw the City in which he lived, falling into ſo much injuſtice and wickedneſs, one day came into the midſt of the City with a Candle in his hand at noon day, and being asked what was his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to come with a candle in his hand at Noon-day, Oh! ſaith he, I come to ſearch every corner of the City narrowly, to ſee if I can find an honeſt man, in ſuch a multitude of men and women he could not find an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man. Now by way of alluſion, is it not ſo at this day? when Jeſus Chriſt comes, <hi>ſhall he find faith upon the earth?</hi> If before Chriſt comes, he ſhould now ſend a Meſsenger with the Candle of the Lord in his hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this City, into the Markets, amongſt the buyers and ſellers; into your ſhops, amongſt the Tradeſ-men. If a man ſhould come with the Candle of the Lord into the Courr of Aldermen, into the Cuſtom-houſe, amongſt thoſe Officers, to all the Committees of Parliament, to the Councell of State, with the Candle of the Lord; and there be looking and eſpying and ſearching; and being asked who do you look for, might he not anſwer. Why if I can find a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> among ſo many <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> if I can find a Diſciple of Jeſus Chriſt amongſt ſuch mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of men and women that cal themſelves Beleevers, that call themſelves Diſciples, but ſurely they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuch, falſly, and in much darkneſs of mind. For now bring the Candle of the Lord, and look, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the difference between the one and the other, and
<pb facs="tcp:114659:17"/>alas! you can hardly find one of an hundred,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vix centeſimus quiſque</hi> was the uſual phraſe of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> upon ſuch occaſions as this. And aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, ſcarce one of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of thoſe that are called and account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtians are ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</note> that are in deed and in truth Chriſtians and Diſciples. This bringeth to remembrance that of the fifth of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> and the firſt verſe. <hi>Run ye to and fro, through the ſtreets of Jeruſalem, and ſee now and know, and ſeek in the broad places thereof, If ye can find a man, if there be any that executeth Iudgement, that ſeek the truth, and I will ſpare it.</hi> Behold here the paucity of true Iſraelites: ſo now My Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſo many Diſciples of Chriſt in the Parliament, ſo many Chriſtians and no more; and ſo many Diſciples, real Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt in Common-Councel, in the City, as there are, ſo many Chriſtians, and no more, not one more. Therefore you had need look to it, you have poſſibly hitherto, that have leaſt cauſe to do ſo, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to your ſelves the moſt honorable title of Chriſtians, and Beleevers, &amp; Proteſtants, &amp; Saints &amp; the like, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as when all thoſe are removed that I ſpake of before, where ſhall you find a man that may be ſo ſtiled?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, Hence you may ſee the miſtakes (and the ſad conſequences of thoſe miſtakes) wherein the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of men in this Nation, and City, and Aſſembly, (for I will keep neer home, and not expatiate abroad) in what miſtakes (and conſequences of ſuch miſtakes) I ſay, are ſuch involved, who confidently aſſume to themſelves, and attribute to each other this honourable <hi>Appellation</hi> of Chriſtians? Do thou ſooth up me, and I will ſooth up thee; Do thou have a charitable good opinion and eſteem of me, and ſo I will have of thee, ſay theſe men one unto another in effect: But now ſee here your errour, and your danger, and the miſtake, and the conſequence of it. What if you ſhould argue <hi>Ex non conceſſis?</hi> what if you ſhould beg the Queſtion, and deſire that may be taken for granted, that is not granted, what wofull miſtaking is here? Suppoſe that you ſay thus of your ſelves, and others ſay thus, that are men,
<pb facs="tcp:114659:18"/>that judge as Chriſt ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> iohn 7.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. rom. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>according to outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> yea, but how if the Head of the Chriſtians, Jeſus Chriſt, the great Doctor of the Chair, ſhould not agree with that determination that thou haſt made, that thou art a Chriſtian? for <hi>he judgeth according to Truth:</hi> What if all the world ſhould call thee ſuch, and at the laſt day Chriſt ſhould before all the world, bid thee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, thou art no Chriſtian, what is the conſequence of ſuch a miſtake as this is? And therefore Chriſtians you had need go upon ſure grounds, and you that are not Chriſtians, or have cauſe to doubt whether you are ſoor no, you had need make enquiry from this day forward. So thou that art an infamons perſon, an odious wretch, for ſordid Luſts, thy throat an open Sepulcher, evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, breathing out Oaths, Curſings, Blaſphemings, thou that haſt thy bones rotting through thine unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and filthineſs, wilt thou take upon thee, the famous and honourable title of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> and a <hi>Beleever,</hi> doſt thou think to carry the cauſe thus? Why Angels and intelligent men ſee cleerly thou art no ſuch perſon, much more doth Jeſus Chriſt ſee it cleerly that is the Head of Chriſtians. Thou takeſt the Name of Chriſtian upon thee, even as the Jeſuites take upon them the Name of Jeſus, it is a ſweet Name, an honorable Name, a name of great reſpect: But now the Jeſuites (that are denominated from Jeſus) aſſuming it to themſelves, they are the hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt men, and the vildeſt perſons in the world, the greateſt ſeducers,
<note place="margin">So <hi>Paul</hi> of the unbeleeving lews, Behold thou art cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Jew, and reſteſt in the Law, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt thy beaſt of God. Rom. 2.17.</note> the moſt bloody and cruel minded men of all the Sects of the Papiſts. Now it will be a ſad caſe at the laſt day for thee to be ranked with theſe men; theſe men they have as good a Name as thou haſt, and as famous and as honourable a Name; as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostome</hi> ſaith of the Name Chriſtian. Yea, but it is not what thou art called but what thou art, that will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into at the laſt day, however thou carrieſt it now. * Behold thou art called a Chriſtian, and reſteſt in that
<pb facs="tcp:114659:18"/>Name, and makeſt thy boaſt of Chriſt; but <hi>thou hast eyes full of Adulterie,</hi> and <hi>thy heart is full of coverous practiſes,</hi> and <hi>thou canst not ceaſe to ſin;</hi> when thou ſinneſt thou rejoyceſt, and then thou art moſt merry and jovial, when there is the greateſt cauſe that thon ſhouldeſt be moſt ſad and diſconſolate. Now what art thou the better for the Name of a Chriſtian, and Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and a Proteſtant, no Papiſt, and the like, if thou be ſuch a baſe wretch, and ſo continueſt to the end? And therefore you had need ſeriouſly to conſider this miſtake, and the ſad conſequences of that miſtake when you ſtile your ſelves Chriſtians, and are not ſo, when you are accounted ſo by others, and are not ſo indeed. But eſpecially I would ſpeak to thoſe that have profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves Chriſtians, and ſo have been taken to be upon a better account than others, in regard of a <hi>form of Godlineſs,</hi> and now are fallen off what a ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are theſe men in, who have rejected the word of Chriſt, deſpiſed the Spirit of Chriſt, ſpeak evil of the Wayes of Chriſt, account the Ordinances of chriſt, vain things, in a word have renounced the whole new Teſtament Unction: and being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by an unclean, blaſphemous Spirit, account it, and call it their Glory, and their perfection to perpetrate the vileſt abominations, without the reluctancy of their own Spirit; what will be the end of theſe men the Apoſtle declares in Heb. 10.26. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r if we ſin willingly after that we have received the know edge of the Truth, there remaineth no more Sacrifice for ſin but a certain fearfull looking for, and expectation of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; fiery indignation, which ſhal devour the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</hi> Give them a portion with Hypocrites, noting to us, that Hypocrites they are the firſt born of Hell, they have the right of <hi>Primo-geniture,</hi> a double portion as it were, give him his portion with Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Now thirdly, Here all men may diſcern as in a
<pb facs="tcp:114659:19"/>Glaſſe, how to judge of themſelves, and what to ſet down by way of account concerning their eſtate, if ſo be that the queſtion be thus put among you, from the greateſt to the leaſt in this Aſſembly, Art thou a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? Yes, But art thou aſſured of it in the power and light of truth? How knoweſt thou, thou art a chriſtian? Why now, here is a glaſſe, whereby thou maieſt diſcern, whereby thou art enabled to enquire and examine out the truth; Why you ſee plainly, that originally, thoſe were called chriſtians, who were indeed Diſciples. <hi>The Diſciples were called Chriſtians firſt in Antioch.</hi> So that now if thou art indeed and in truth a <hi>Diſciple</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, thou art a <hi>chriſtian.</hi> But if thou art none of chriſts Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, but either <hi>Moſes</hi> Diſciple, or <hi>Mammons</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, if thou art a ſervant to the God of this world, thon art an enemy to chriſt inſtead of being a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, an enemy to his Intereſt, ſecretly wiſhing and deſiring that this Intereſt that is now ſetting up in the world might be undermined and brought to Inought And if thou haſt not the ſelf-ſame Spirit dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thee that dwelt in Jeſus Chriſt? If thon art act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Spirit of ſelf-love a Spirit of vain Glory, thou art none of Chriſts, his glorious unction, is not yet pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon thee. Haſt thou learned and walked in the way of the Lord, for, he that ſaith, he abideth in him ought ſo to walk, even as he walked, if not, with what face canſt thou challenge to thy ſelf the the name of his Diſciple; Oh conſider I ſay again, what little cauſe thou haſt to aſſume to thy ſelf the name of a chriſtian.</p>
            <p>If ſo be that you ſhould ſee a man with his face and his feet contrary each to other, his face look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upward, forward and upward unto Heaven, and his feet directly turned backward, carrying him backward, downward toward a ſteep precipice
<pb facs="tcp:114659:19"/>under which is a pit of deſtruction, Firſt you would ſay this is a Monſter, this is a Monſter, his face one way, and his feet walking another, and leading him backward: And then ſecondly, you would pity him, he is going to deſtruction, and ſees it not, ſees not the precipice, he ſees not the pit, the Gulf of deſtruction underneath, at the bottom of that precipice, you would ſay he is a Monſter and you would pity him. My Brethren this is directly the Deſcription of a <hi>Counterfeit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;</hi> here is a Character now, of abundance of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the world, and I fear of many here preſent, It is true your faces are fixed upwards and toward hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, towards Chriſt, towards God, happineſs, ſalvation, you look that way, you profeſs that way, look in your face, it is a beautifull face, and it is ſet the right way towards Heaven and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, towards God and his Glory, this is your pretence, but look down now upon your feet, and obſerve your walking, your fect are turned clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to your face, and theſe feet carrying the body, face, and pretence, and all to Hell, and utter ruine and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſuch a man is a <hi>Monster</hi> amongſt men, and not a kindly <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that is rightly born &amp; rightly begotten of the immortal ſeed of the Word, born of God and not of man, he is not ſuch a man, but a <hi>Monſter</hi> amongſt Chriſtians. And ah, poor <hi>Monſter</hi> whither art thou going, walking, carrying, and drawing thy very face, thy preſence, and pretence and demeanour together with thee, down that precipice to eternall deſtruction. Now although it is true, I cannot determine, which are theſe in this Aſſembly, yet he that ſits in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and obſerves all your down-lyings and upriſings, and underſtands your thoughts a farre off, he ſees how many <hi>monstrous Chriſtians</hi> there are in the world, and here, with their faces towards Heaven, and their feet turned and diſtorted directly contrary to them.
<pb facs="tcp:114659:20"/>And therefore it is that in the Miniſtery of the word this day, he calls out to thoſe <hi>Monsters</hi> of <hi>Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> that have a beautifull face, a fair pretence and their actions contrary. Take heed, whither are you going, and look after the Precipice, the downfall, the gulf of ruine that is behind you, and that you are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, and therefore now remember this truth, this glaſs ſhews to you who are Chriſtians, who are not, who are Monſters, who have neither the face, nor any thing, no not any proportion of a Chriſtian, and who they are that have any part. No more Chriſtians in this congregation than Diſciples, and ſo many of you as are indeed the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt, ſo many may deſervedly challenge the Title, the Name, and honourable Appellation of Chriſtians, But I muſt draw to a concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> In the laſt place therefore; Fourthly. It is a <hi>word of Exhortation</hi> to thoſe that are <hi>Chriſtians indeed,</hi> as you know there were <hi>Iews</hi> or <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, it concerns you, and it concerns your Head, your high Prieſt (as Chriſt is called, the Apoſtle, and the high Prieſt of our profeſſion, in the third of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and the firſt. <hi>Wherefore holy Brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, conſider the Apoſtle, and high-Priest of our Profeſſion, Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>) Why now it concerns you to be Chriſtians indeed, and to purpoſe, not onely to be ſo, but to be ſo in the ſight of men, as wel as in the ſight of God, that tries the hearts. Art thou a Chriſtian cordially, cordially ingaged into the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Jeſus Chriſt? Haſt thou received this truth? Deſireſt to be in the world, as Chriſt was in the world, and not to be of the world, any more then Chriſt was of the world? doſt thou act from the ſame principles, from the ſame Spirit in all thy carriage and converſation? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en <hi>Christians</hi> live like your ſelves? Be in behaviour
<pb facs="tcp:114659:20"/>as it becometh the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt; for the time is comming that thoſe that are <hi>true Chriſtians</hi> ſhall lift up their Heads when the reſt of the world ſhal hide theirs, and hang them down.</p>
            <p>There were four Monarchies, and all of them are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by their ſeverall titles, ending like unto this, <hi>Caldeans</hi> and <hi>Babylonians, Perſians, Grecians, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> why now the ſecond extinguiſhed the firſt, and ſwallowed up the very name of it, the third,
<note place="margin">Daniel a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 34.44.</note> extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſecond, and the fourth the third, and ſo they have ſupplanted each other. Now comes the fifth Monarch the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> with his <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> and ſets up a new-Government in the world, makes a new Heaven, and a new Earth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms all things, and then as the name of the Romans was honourable in their time, ſo ſhall the name of Chriſtians be the honourableſt name that ever was upon earth, ſince the firſt Monarchy &amp; before, and all other <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> ſhal be but <hi>Infamy,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Honour</hi> that ſhal reſt upon <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> &amp; his <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the world, &amp; that upon a voluntary acknowledgment &amp; confeſſion of many of the Nations of the Earth, &amp; thoſe that refuſe to ſet up this Kingdom, ſhal be made Tributaries to it at leaſt, Nay,
<note place="margin">Iſaiah 60.12.</note> that Nation and Kingdome that will not ſerve Chriſt and <hi>Christians</hi> ſhall periſh, yea thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall be utterly waſted: All the Dominions under the whole Heaven ſhall be given to the Saints of the moſt high, and even now the time,
<note place="margin">Daniel. 7.27</note> and times and half a time is almoſt finiſhed, as it is in the 10th of the <hi>Revel:</hi> Time ſhal be no longer then the beginning of the ſound of the ſeveneth Angell,
<note place="margin">Rev. 11.15</note> and then the Kingdomes of the world, ſhall become the Lords and his Chriſts and his Saints, even theirs that are with him choſen and called and faithfull, and they ſhall walk with him in white; for they are worthy, and who then but Chriſt and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the world. Now is the beginning of the dawning
<pb facs="tcp:114659:21"/>of that glorious day, and therefore Chriſtians lift up your Heads, fear not all the Invaſions, Inſurrections, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> againſt <hi>Christ,</hi> they are as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, they are but as ropes of ſand, all their Counſels ſhal come to nought, and whatſoever they agree on in their Councill Chambers, they ſhal never perform in the field, And therefore ye <hi>Christians</hi> ſtand faſt in that liberty, with which Chriſt hath made you free, cleave cloſe to that glorious truth of the Goſpell;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> He made him to be ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God in him, and walk in holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord. Remember what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Spirit ſaid to any of the Churches,
<note place="margin">Rev. 2, &amp; 3.</note> he ſaith to all the Saints. <hi>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches. To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth and holdeth out to the end, ſhal be given a Crown of life, and thus and thus he ſhall be rewarded.</hi> And therefore now, upon the defection and Apoſtacy of others, do you approve your ſelves unto Chriſt, and not onely ſo, but approve your ſelves in the world, like the Sons of God, and daughters of God, and like the anointed of the Lord, as having received a great meaſure of that Anointing, the Spirit being poured out richly upon you, even the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt. All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirits and Intereſts will be aſhamed, and go out like as the leſſer ſtars go out and hide themſelves from the riſing Sun, and the name of Chriſt and his Diſciples ſhall be famous from the riſing of the Sun to the going down of the ſame, and ſuch honour ſhall Chriſt and all his Saints have, when he comes, <hi>Amen</hi> come Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, come quickly. But this ſhall ſuffice for this time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:114659:21"/>
            <opener>To prevent errors in reading, the Evrrata's in Printing are thus to be rectified.</opener>
            <head type="sub">ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN the ſheet of <hi>B,</hi> page 8. line 14. for <hi>weie</hi> tead <hi>were.</hi> C p. 3. l. 4. for <hi>tween</hi> r. <hi>between.</hi> D p. 2. l. 26. for <hi>abode they die</hi> r. <hi>abode, and when they die.</hi> p. 7. l. 3. for <hi>richest</hi> r. <hi>rich.</hi> p. 8. l. 5. for <hi>whereever</hi> r. <hi>where ever,</hi> E p. 1. l. 37. for <hi>Altheiſts</hi> r, <hi>Atheiſts.</hi> P. 4. l. 11. for <hi>ſoor</hi> r. <hi>ſo or.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for literal faults in Printing, the favour and help of the Reader is requeſted, according to custome of courteous dealing in ſuch caſes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
